<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section id="im_file">
  <title>File (im_file)</title>
  <para>
    This module can be used to read log messages from files. The file position can be 
    persistently saved across restarts in order to avoid reading from the beginning again
    when nxlog is restarted.
    It also supports external rotation tools. When the module cannot read any more data
    from the file, it checks whether the opened file descriptor belongs to the
    same filename it opened originally. If the inodes differ, the module assumes the file was
    moved and reopens its input.
  </para>
  <para>
    im_file uses a 1 second interval to monitor files for new messages. This method was
    implemented because polling a regular file is not supported on all platforms.
    If there is no more data to read, the module will sleep for 1 second.
  </para>
  <para>
    By using wildcards, the module can read multiple files simultaneously and will open
    new files as they appear. It will also enter newly created directories if recursion
    is enabled.
  </para>

  <section id="im_file_config">
    <title>Configuration</title>
    <para>
      In addition to the <link linkend="config_module_common">common module directives</link>,
      the following can be used to configure the im_file module instance.
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><anchor id="im_file_config_file"/>File</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This mandatory directive specifies the name of the input file to open.
	      It must be a <link linkend="lang_type_string">string</link> type
	      <link linkend="lang_expressions">expression</link>.
	      For relative filenames you should be aware that nxlog changes its working
	      directory to '/' unless the global
	      <link linkend="config_global_spooldir">SpoolDir</link> is set to something else.
	      On Windows systems the directory separator is backslash. For compatibility reasons
	      the forward slash '/' character can be also used as the directory separator,
	      but this only works for filenames which don't contain wildcards. If the
	      filename is specified using wildcards, you should use backslash for the directory
	      separator.
	      </para>
	    <para>
	      Wildcards are supported in filenames only, directory names in the path cannot
	      be wildcarded. Wildcards are not regular expressions, these are patterns commonly
	      used by unix shells to expand filenames which is also known as globbing.
	      <variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>?</term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Matches a single character only.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>*</term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Matches zero or more characters.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>\*</term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Matches the asterisk '*' character.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>\?</term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Matches the question mark '?' character.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>[...]</term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Used to specify a single character. If the first character of the class
		      description is ^ or !, the sense of the description is reversed.
		      The rest of the class description is a list of single characters or pairs
		      of characters separated by -. Any of those characters can have a backslash
		      in front of them, which is ignored; this lets you use the characters ]
		      and - in the character class, as well as ^ and ! at the beginning.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	      </variablelist>
	      <note>
		<para>
		  The backslash character '\' is used to escape the wildcard
		  characters, unfortunately this is the same as the directory separator on Windows.
		  Take this into account when specifying wildcarded filenames on this platform.
		  Lets suppose that we have log files under the directory <filename>C:\test</filename>
		  which need to be monitored. Specifying the wildcard <replaceable>'C:\test\*.log'</replaceable>
		  will not match because '\*' becomes a literal asterisk, thus it is treated as a
		  non-wildcarded filename. For this reason the directory separator needs to be escaped,
		  so the <replaceable>'C:\test\\*.log'</replaceable> will match our files. 
		  <replaceable>'C:\\test\\*.log'</replaceable> will also work.
		  When specifying the filename using double quotes, this would became 
		  <replaceable>"C:\\test\\\\*.log"</replaceable> because the backslash is also
		  used as an escape character inside double quoted 
		  <link linkend="lang_literal_string">string literals</link>.
		  Filenames on Windows systems are treated case-insensitively. Unix/Linux is case-sensitive.
		</para>
	      </note>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><anchor id="im_file_config_savepos"/>SavePos</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <simpara>
	      This directive takes a boolean value of TRUE or FALSE and specifies whether
	      the file position should be saved when nxlog exits.
	      The file position will be read from the cache file file upon startup.	      
	      The file position is saved by default if this directive is not specified
	      in the configuration.
	      Even if SavePos is enabled, it can be explicitly turned off with the
	      <link linkend="config_global_nocache">NoCache</link> directive.
	    </simpara>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><anchor id="im_file_config_readfromlast"/>ReadFromLast</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <simpara>
	      This optional directive takes a boolean value. If it is set to TRUE, it instructs
	      the module to only read logs which arrived after nxlog was started in case the
	      saved position could not be read (for example on first start).
	      When SavePos is TRUE and a previously saved position value could be read,
	      the module will resume reading from this saved position.
	      If this is FALSE, the module will read all logs from the file. This can result
	      in quite a lot of messages which is usually not the expected behaviour.
	      If this directive is not specified, it defaults to TRUE.
	    </simpara>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><anchor id="im_file_config_recursive"/>Recursive</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <simpara>
	      This directive takes a boolean value of TRUE or FALSE and specifies whether
	      input files should be searched recursively under subdirectories.
	      The default value is TRUE.
	      This option takes effect only if wildcards are used in the filename.
	      For example if '/var/log/*.log' is specified in the
	      <link linkend="im_file_config_file">File</link> directive, then 
	      '/var/log/apache2/access.log' will also match.
	      Because wildcards in directory names of the path are not supported, this directive
	      makes it possible to read  multiple files from different subdirectories
	      with a single im_file module instance only.
	    </simpara>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><anchor id="im_file_config_pollinterval"/>PollInterval</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <simpara>
	      This directive specifies in seconds how frequently the module will check for
	      new files and new log entries. If this directive is not specified it defaults 
	      to 1 second.
	      Fractional seconds may be specified, i.e. to check twice every second you should
	      set the following: <replaceable>PollInterval 0.5</replaceable>
	    </simpara>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term><anchor id="im_file_config_inputtype"/>InputType</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <simpara>
	      See the description about <link linkend="config_inputtype">InputType</link>
	      in the global module config section.
	    </simpara>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </section>

  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../../apidoc-im_file.xml" />

  <section id="im_file_config_examples">
    <title>Configuration examples</title>
    <para>
      <example>
	<title>Forwarding logs from a file to a remote host</title>
	<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../../../config-examples/config-example-im_file.xml" />
      </example>
    </para>
  </section>

</section>
